Robert D Allen, MBA

Director of MarTech

LinkedIn.com/in/RobertDAllenMBA

Seattle, WA | Miami, FL 512-666-7539 Contact@RDAMBA.com

Incorrigible optimist and irredeemable punster, I believe nothing is impossible with sufficient humility and creativity.

My career has been defined by bringing order to chaos, righting the ship, and snatching victory from the jaws of defeat. Prior to my shift to Amazon I spent ten years running a tech startup in San Francisco and a digital marketing agency out of Austin Texas. I sold my company in 2018.

My focus is on intentionality, whether buildin a team culture of humility and experimentation or deconstructing decades of operational bloat. With 15 years of people management and 12 years across product, marketing, and product marketing, not much surprises me anymore. It is my position that data should drive everything, exceptional customer experience is non-negotiable, and business value can be grown in a desert if tended properly.

Work Experience

Director of MarTech

Discover Financial Services – Chicago, IL – Mar 2022 to Current

MarTech at Discover did not exist prior to 2021. I was the third person to lead the MarTech product team and in many ways the org still did not exist. I joined to find that we had a reputation for broken promises, a balloon budget based on those promises which we would never have been able to deliver against, and 17 other teams self-serving their MarTech needs in our absence. It was like Christmas for me. My priority was earning trust, which we did through radical transparency and partnership. By training our product managers on first principles we were able to begin delivering value almost immediately.

In Q2 we developed an operating model, I provided and coordinated training for our product managers, and we were able to attract three excellent Directors of Product to lead our Product Families for AdTech, Data Collection, and Marketing Capabilities. The quarter was capped with my presentation of our roadmap to an SVP and C-Suite audience.

In Q3 we began delivering on our first work, hosted our first product family roadshows, finished our financial review, and participated in the company-wide leadership planning series.

In Q4 we began integrating our team with several enterprise marketing teams, bringing our roadmaps and engagement models into closer alignment. Our Year-In-Review document showed we delivered \$11mm in incremental PBT, which was the first value delivered by MarTech at Discover.

Head of Technical Marketing

Amazon, Consumer Payments – Seattle, WA – Jun 2020 to Feb 2022

Consumer Payments is the cash register of Amazon retail. We own all payment methods and the checkout experience. My team in particular was responsible for building a risk mitigation program which had no customer value but was worth billions to Amazon. The team I inherited had 6 staff but would rapidly grow to 45.

We operated in close collaboration with Business Intelligence, Product Managers, and Technical Program Managers. We developed new methods of inferring Voice of Customer to drive continuous improvement. I personally designed a new multivariate testing program which was central to the success of the program, generating thousands of permutations with just dozens of assets, with results able to be easily parsed via Pivot table.

Our remit expanded from just the US in 2021 to a full 13 countries globally in Q1 2022. I managed the TPMs who owned the marketing teams for each country, from Germany to Singapore. My team and I had the ambitious task of building out our multivariate testing program for 8 campaigns in all 13 countries in just 6 months. We delivered exactly on target, with training videos, walkthroughs, demos, and hands-on training for the newly hired marketing teams for each country.

By the numbers: I uncovered an attribution oversight which gave us a 59.8% lift in conversions in month 2. My multivariate testing program enabled broad marketing copy testing which increased zero-cost conversions by 22.8% and cut our cost per acquisition by 42.0%. My team drove 78% of conversions for the global program. We achieved our goal and wrapped the program just 18 months after I joined.

Head of Email Development

Holland America Line – Seattle, WA – Nov 2019 to May 2020

HAL and Seabourn use HTML modules for building emails. Their process took 8 hours per email. I led an optimization process which automated email building via a simple form, reducing email development to 15 minutes per campaign. My team then in-housed a series of highly interactive email elements which saved the brands \$40k each. When covid hit, the company halted all operations and laid off most staff, including my team.

Manager, Product Marketing

Amazon, Key by Amazon – Seattle, WA – Nov 2018 to Oct 2019

The Key team provides secure in-home delivery of all Amazon products. Our portfolio includes smart door locks, a partnership with several car brands, Chamberlain smart garage doors, and a B2B offering for apartment complexes.

I owned launching the Key for Garage and Key for Business product lines. The Key for Garage launch achieved 20% of the annual sales goal for the entire Amazon Key org in 2 weeks, and sold more units in that time than Key for Home sold in 18 months. The Head of Marketing described my launch as "the most extensive marketing we have ever done."

Founder

Splash Mktg - Austin, TX - Feb 2015 to Oct 2018

Splash Mktg served 30 clients as their full marketing and IT departments. We developed brands, web apps, digital services, negotiated 3p contracts and partnerships, crafted local and national campaign strategies, optimized tech stacks, and offered staff augmentation services. I sold the company to our largest client in 2018.

Founder

Fit In Today PBC – San Francisco, CA – Sep 2010 to Jan 2015

We found a way to reduce new hire turnover, improve the average quality of job applicants, and reduce the cost of recruiting. The company failed for many small reasons and a few large ones, but ultimately my inexperience was central in our failure to achieve greatness.

Education

Master of Business Administration

Rochester Institute of Technology - Rochester, NY

My program covered a wide range of topics, including accounting, finance, marketing, operations, strategy, and leadership. The program involved a combination of classroom instruction, practical experience, and case studies. The RIT MBA program allowed me to specialize in three particular areas of business, being Product Commercialization, Technology Management, and Entrepreneurship.

Product commercialization is a cross of product management and product marketing. We delved into the process of bringing a new product or service to market, validating customer needs via market research, partnering with engineering, intellectual property, manufacturing and distribution, and selling and support.

Technology management is the process of overseeing and organizing the use of technology within an organization to achieve its goals and objectives. It involves planning, acquiring, implementing, and maintaining software and technology systems, as well as staying up to date with emerging technologies. Technology management requires a strong understanding of current and future technologies, as well as strong project management and leadership skills.

Entrepreneurship requires a range of skills, including strategic thinking, innovation, leadership, communication, financial management, marketing and sales, and knowing when to pivot. Developing these skills takes time and effort, but mostly personal experience, so the program was highly experiential. Becoming better able to identify opportunities, assess risks, and develop a plan for success only cover the lofty half. The long-tail half is learning to inspire and motivate a team, communicate vision and goals effectively, manage and allocate resources effectively, and adapt to changes in the market. The program never truly ends, it just leaves the classroom.